Guide to the Frank Waters Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Frank Waters Papers
1929-2006
1950-2006
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Waters, Frank
SWWC.137
5 Linear Feet
6 boxes
This collection contains papers by and about Frank Waters and some associates connected to Waters. The bulk of the collection concerns papers related to the Frank Waters Foundation and its activities. The collection is organized into six series: Correspondence, Writings by Frank Waters, Writings about Frank Waters, The Frank Waters Foundation, Frank Waters' Associates, Other Writings, Oversized, and Artifacts.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mary Torrence, 2017.
Biographical Note
Frank Waters was born in Colorado Springs, Colorado on July 25, 1902. He felt a deep connection with the geographic area known as the American Southwest that could be seen in many of his writings. His works were inspired by this deep connection of this geographic area in addition to many other topics and themes related to the American Southwest. Over the course of his lifetime, Waters wrote and published over 25 books, in addition to other works, beginning early on his life, when his short story "How It Was Settled" was first published in 1916 when Waters was fourteen. While Waters wrote many influential books and other written works, he is probably best known for his book The Man Who Killed the Deer, which was published in 1942.
Waters spent most of his life in New Mexico, particularly in Arroyo Seco, where he moved to after working for the office of Inter-American Affairs in Washington D.C. in the early 1940s. In addition to his writings, Waters was also the editor of El Crepusculo, a Spanish-English newspaper that operates out of Taos, New Mexico from 1949 to 1951 and book reviewer for the Saturday Review of Literature from 1950 to 1956. In 1992, the Frank Waters Foundation was established in his name with the idea of encouraging literary and artistic advancement in the spirit of Frank Waters and for the American Southwest. Much of the Frank Waters Papers is related to the efforts of this organization. Waters died at the age of 92 in Arroyo Seco, New Mexico on June 3,1995.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains papers by and about Frank Waters and some associates connected to Waters. The bulk of the collection concerns papers related to the Frank Waters Foundation and its activities. The collection is organized into six series: Correspondence, Writings by Frank Waters, Writings about Frank Waters, The Frank Waters Foundation, Frank Waters' Associates, Other Writings, Oversized, and Artifacts.
Series 1, Correspondence (box 1), includes letters to and from Frank Waters, as well as correspondence of Barbara Waters. Spans 1948 - 2006, organized chronologically.
Series 2, Writings by Frank Waters (box 1), contains various writings from 1950 - 1993, with the bulk spanning from 1950 - 1951 with some undated materials. This series also includes photocopies of El Crepusculo from 1950 - 1951 during which time Frank Waters was editor. Items are arranged chronologically.
Series 3, Writings about Frank Waters (box 1), concerns various writings about Frank Waters and his works. This includes, but is not limited to, articles about Frank Waters, reviews of his works, memorial articles discussing the life and legacy of Waters. Items are arranged chronologically.
Series 4, Frank Waters Foundation (box 2 - 4), comprises the bulk of the collection and contains materials related to the Frank Waters Foundation and the Frank Waters Society. This series is further subdivided into five subseries: Operations, Newsletters, Website, Tributes, and Conferences/Workshops. Operations contains various operational materials including a master list of members as of September 2005. Newsletters are dated from 1993-2006. The Website subseries contains a printout of the Sheltering the Creative Spirit as it appeared as of January 23, 2002. The Tributes subseries concerns materials related to events held in Frank Waters' honor such as invitations and itineraries of the events. Finally, the Conferences/Workshops contain materials concerning academic conferences such as Studies in Frank Waters (1982 - 1992), and other workshops at least partly organized by the Frank Waters Foundation. All materials are organized chronologically within their subseries.
Series 5, Frank Waters' Associates (box 4), concerns materials associated with Frank Waters and the Frank Waters Foundation, Alexander Blackburn, Geoffrey and Mary Torrence, and Barbara Waters, Frank Waters' wife. These are organized chronologically within their grouping.
Series 6, Other Writings (box 4), contains writings that do not specifically address Frank Waters, but are related to themes and other topics of interest within the collection.
Series 7, Oversized (box 5), comprises of three photographs of Frank Waters, photocopies of El Crepusculo from September 1949 - December 1950, a copy of Tempo from July 1992.
Series 8, Artifacts (box 6), consists of five bronze statues, including one of his face and two of his writing hand.
Notes to Researchers
The University of New Mexico houses The Frank Waters Papers, 1892-1992 at the University Libraries, Center for Southwest Research
Index Terms
Subjects
Environmental literature
- Correspondence, 1948, 1956, 1987-2006
  Series Description
  Correspondence (box 1), Includes correspondence of Frank Waters, as well as letters to and from Barbara Waters. Spans 1948 - 2006, organized chronologically.
  - Letter to Rowena Meyers from Frank Waters, July 24, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter to Cedric From Ansel, With a Picture of Yosemite National Park on the Opposite Page, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and photos to Mary Ann and Geoffrey Torrence, 1987-2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence filled with cards and Photos to Mary Ann Torrence, October 12, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence to Barbara Waters from Alexander Blackburn, July 21, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Writings by Frank Waters, 1950-1951, 1993
  Contains various writings from 1950 - 1993, with the bulk spanning from 1950 - 1951 with some undated materials. This series also includes photocopies of El Crepusculo from 1950 - 1951 during which time Frank Waters was editor. Items are arranged chronologically.
  - The Boomsbury Review; a book Magazine, with a photo of Frank Waters on the front, June 1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Magic of Seekers of the Fleece by Frank Waters, pgs. 53+55, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Articles and Clippings from El Crepusculo Newspaper, 1950-1951, undated
    - D-303, D-304, D-306, D-307, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - January 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - April 1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - May 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - June 1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - September 1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - General, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - January 1951 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - February 1951 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - March 1951 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - April 1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - May 1951 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - June 1951 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - July 1951 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - August 1951 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - September 1951 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - October 1951 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - November 1951 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - December 1951 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - "Masks Without Meanings" by Frank Waters, Signed by Frank Waters, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Writings About Frank Waters, 1974-2006
  Concerns various writings about Frank Waters and his works. This includes, but is not limited to, articles about Frank Waters, reviews of his works, memorial articles discussing the life and legacy of Waters. Items are arranged chronologically.
  - "The Troops" with a written statement from Barbara Waters on the front page, pgs. 101-109, February 28, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "A Writer's Landscape, Personalities of the West," Lawrence Powell in Westways, January 1974 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "Pure Waters," Joseph Dispenza, pgs. 36-41, September 15, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "Environmental Concerns of Frank Waters," Charles L. Adams, April 8, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Ohio University Press, opened on page three with information on a book called A Sunrise Brighter Still, The Visionary Novels of Frank Waters, Fall 1991 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - New Mexico's Newsmonthly; Crosswinds, Volume IV, Number 1, November 1991 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Article with a portrait of Frank Waters, The Taos News, November 14, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
  - Five Hoka Hey Newspapers, Summer Issue, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Albuquerque Journal and Taos News, June 1992- 1997 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Tiempo, June 2, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - A poem for Frank Waters Written by Victor di Suvero, June 9, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - "Family and Friends Saying Goodbye to Frank Waters," The Taos News, June 15, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - "Perspective", July 1, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Pasa Tiempo Santa Fe, New Mexican, November 1, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Arts and Entertainment Magazine of the Taos News: Tempo, July 25-31, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - "The Duality of Power," with email Correspondence from John, August 18, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Taos is Entirely Special, article by Sawnie Morris, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Order form for Of Time and Change a Memoir, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The Essence of Good Writing, pgs. 1-10, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Borderlands and Transfigurations: Desert Mysticism in Frank Waters,'" The Lizard Woman, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Roads of Transmission" by John Nizalowski, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Frank Waters Foundation, 1985-2006
  This series the bulk of the collection and contains materials related to the Frank Waters Foundation and the Frank Waters Society. This series is further subdivided into five subseries: Operations, Newsletters, Website, Tributes, and Conferences/Workshops. Operations contains various operational materials including a master list of members as of September 2005.
  Newsletters are dated from 1993-2006. The Website subseries contains a printout of the Sheltering the Creative Spirit as it appeared as of January 23, 2002. The Tributes subseries concerns materials related to events held in Frank Waters' honor such as invitations and itineraries of the events.
  Finally, the Conferences/Workshops contain materials concerning academic conferences such as Studies in Frank Waters (1982 - 1992), and other workshops at least partly organized by the Frank Waters Foundation. All materials are organized chronologically within their subseries.
  - Operations, 2000-2005
    - "Roads of Transmission" by John Nizalowski, September 7, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Land map printout, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Sheltering the Creative Spirit," Brochures, Calendar of Events, Photos, and a paper to order a book Memoir, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Thank you cards to contributors, and empty envelopes, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Newsletter, Sheltering the Creative Spirit, 1993-2006
    - July 1997 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - August 1993 - Sept. 2006 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
    - Pages 1-33, January 23, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Letter written by Barbara Waters, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Website, Sheltering the Creative Spirit, 1997, 2002
    - Printout of the online website with photos, November 1, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "Site Index", pgs. 1-10, January 23, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "Horses & Land", pgs. 1-5, January 23, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "Land Trust Letter" article, pgs. 1-7, January 23, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "The Frank Waters Foundation" article, pgs. 1-4, January 23, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "Author Index", pgs. 1-6, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Mission Statement", pgs. 1-5, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - "F. Waters Biography", pgs. 1-4, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - "Centennial", pgs. 1-5, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - "Speeches", pgs. 1-9, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "On Writing", pgs. 1-10, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - "Lyon's Anthology", pgs. 1-3, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "Reviews", pgs. 1-4, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - "Photo Album", pgs. 1-3, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "Frank/Land", pgs. 1-2, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - "Arroyo Seco", pgs. 1-3, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "Out and About", pgs. 1-3, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "Fun and Fun pt. 2", pgs. 1-5, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - "Memorial", pgs. 1-5, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "Artist in Residence", pgs. 1-3, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "B. Waters' Biography", pgs. 1-3, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "B. Waters' Book Review", pgs. 1-6, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - "R. Redford", pgs. 1-2, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - "Tributes to Frank", January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 19-25)
    - "Waters' Park and Waters' Park 2", pgs. 1-4, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - "S.W. Writing Award and Awardees", pgs. 1-5, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Friends", pgs. 1-6, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - "Frank's Car", pgs. 1-5, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - "Opera", pgs. 1-2, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - "Fundraising", pgs. 1-4, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - "Open Forum", pgs. 1-5, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - "Bronzes", pgs. 1-3, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - "Store", pgs. 1-5, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - "Contacts & Links", pgs. 1-3, January 23, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Tributes to Frank Waters, 1982, 2002
    - UNM Appraisal Visit No. 1, newsletter, Barbara Waters letter, February 11, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Invitation to "A Tribute to Frank Waters" Annual Dinner and Meeting, March 29, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Invitation to the Frank Waters Centennial Celebration, along with an itinerary, and motel accommodations, July 28, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Itinerary for a memorial celebrating Frank Waters' Life, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Itinerary for a memorial celebrating Frank Waters' Life, with handwritten notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Studies in Frank Waters - V: The Papers from "Frank Waters: Western Mystic, December 29, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Conferences and Workshops, 1985-2005
    - Studies in Frank Waters - VII: The Papers from "An Appreciation", October 19, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Studies in Frank Waters - VIII: The Papers from "Emergences", October 18, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Studies in Frank Waters - IX: Printout and papers from "Flight from Fiesta", October 17, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
    - Studies in Frank Waters - X: The Papers from "Connections", October 22, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Studies in Frank Waters - XIV: "The People", October 1992 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Website printout of the November Frank Waters Lecture Series, held at the Millicent Rogers Museum, November 17, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - An article titled "Healing Ways", August 23, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Itinerary for "Healing Ways: Seeking Common Threads" conference, August 26-28, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - The Frank Waters Foundation, Sheltering the Creative Spirit: "Nurturing the Creative Spirit" paper, workshop schedule, & map, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Associates of Frank Waters, 1980-2006
  This series concerns materials associated with Frank Waters and the Frank Waters Foundation, Alexander Blackburn, Geoffrey and Mary Torrence, and Barbara Waters, Frank Waters' wife. These are organized chronologically within their grouping.
  - Email correspondence from Alex Blackburn, Editor, Writers' Forum, To writers and scholars, January 6, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Alex's speech of acceptance for his award titled, pgs. 1-13, April 9, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - A Book Magazine; The Bloomsbury Review, Volume 26 Issue 4, July/August 2006 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Santo Domingo Corn Dance lyrics, Written on the front "for Frank Waters", undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence to Mary Ann Torrence, June 1980-1995 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Two Correspondence to Mary Ann Torrence on receiving the Frank Waters Foundation: Sheltering the Creative Spirit, Newsletter, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - A Correspondence to Professor Sture Allen, From Mrs. Geoffrey Torrence of Athena School, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - "Home and Away" Poem for Barbara Waters in Memory of Frank, June 9, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - XI. Mountains, with "From one changing woman to another. Barbara Waters" written on the front, , February 28, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Other Writings, 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  Contents
  New Mexico's Newsmonthly: Crosswinds, Volume IV, Number IV March/April 1992 Journeys: A Literary Magazine, with Frank Waters pictured on the front, Spring 1993 Hoka Hey Winter Issue, 1990
- Oversized Materials, 1949-1950, 1992, undated
  This series comprises oversized photographs and newspapers reelating to Frank Waters.
  - Photographs, 2001, undated
    - Frank Waters with anu girl, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Frank Waters with three unknown people, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Framed Photograph of Frank Waters with a check at the bottom, October 30th, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Newspapers, 1949-1950, 1992
    - El Crepusculo newspaper (photocopies), September 1949 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - El Crepusculo newspaper (photocopies), October 1949 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - El Crepusculo newspaper (photocopies), November 1949 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - El Crepusculo newspaper (photocopies), December 1949 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - El Crepusculo newspaper (photocopies), December 22, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - El Crepusculo newspaper (photocopies), February 1950 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - El Crepusculo newspaper (photocopies), March 1950 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - El Crepusculo newspaper (photocopies), July 1950 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - El Crepusculo newspaper (photocopies), August 1950 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - El Crepusculo newspaper (photocopies), October 1950 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - El Crepusculo newspaper (photocopies), November 1950 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - El Crepusculo newspaper (photocopies), December 1950 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Tempo Newspaper with a picture of Frank Waters on the Front Page, July 23, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Artifacts, undated
  This series contains artifacts relating to Frank Waters.
  - Sculpture: Hand with Pen, undated (Box 6, Item 1)
  - Sculpture: Centennial Medallion, undated (Box 6, Item 2)
  - Sculpture: Hand, undated (Box 6, Item 3)
  - Sculpture: Face, undated (Box 6, Item 4)
  - Sculpture: Rock, undated (Box 6, Item 5)